Welcome to the BATbern Event Management Platform! Today I'll show you how to plan an event without losing your mind.
We'll go through the complete event lifecycle, from "Oh no, we need an event!" to "Finally over, off to the archive!" In this video, you'll see all the important steps an organizer takes to plan a Berner Architekten Treffen, without panicking.
We begin at the Event Dashboard.
This is basically your command center, where you keep track of all events you've ever organized or will organize in the future.
Authentication via AWS Cognito is already done.
You can see your username in the top right, and with that, you have the power to use all functions as an organizer.
With great power comes great responsibility!
Now let's create a brand new event! Click the "New Event" button in the top right. Boom! A modal form appears.
Don't worry, it looks like a lot, but we'll fill it out together.
Event Number. A unique identifier for this event.
The system internally uses the format "BATbern" followed by the number. Basically the birth certificate of your event.
This serves for identification in the database and in URLs.
Title. Here comes the name that should excite your participants!
"Boring Architecture Event Number 47" would be honest, but maybe not the best choice.
Choose something meaningful that people will see on the public website.
Description. A brief explanation of the event topic.
This information helps interested people understand why they absolutely should register.
Or at least what it's all about.
Event Type. Choose between three formats: "Evening" for after-work events, where you can network a bit after work.
"Afternoon" for afternoon sessions, perfect for those who prefer to be on the couch in the evening.
Or "Full Day" for all-day conferences. You'll need lots of coffee for that! This affects scheduling and slot management.
Date and Registration Deadline. The event date determines when the event takes place.
Please choose a date in the future, we don't support time travel yet.
The registration deadline is important for participant management.
Venue. Name and address of the venue. So not "in my basement," but a real place with an address.
This information will be displayed on the public website so people can actually find their way there.
We click "Save" and the event is created. Tada! The system automatically returns to the dashboard, and there it is!
Your brand new event in the list. Your baby is born!
After event creation, we navigate to the event detail page. Here we can assign tasks to team members.
Because why should you do everything alone when you have a whole team? Click "Edit" to open the event form again.
Switch to the "Tasks" tab. Here you see a predefined list of standard tasks that come up with every event.
The system knows its stuff, it knows what needs to be done.
For each task, we select a responsible organizer from the dropdown menu.
This ensures that all important activities are clearly assigned and nothing gets forgotten.
Because forgotten tasks lead to chaos, and chaos leads to... well, more chaos.
After assigning, we click "Save". The system saves all tasks and returns to the event detail page. Perfect!
To review the tasks, we navigate to the task list.
First you see the default filter "My Tasks," which only shows your own tasks.
But we're curious and want to know what the others are up to.
We change the filter to "All Tasks" to see all assignments.
This gives an overview of responsibilities across the entire team. And who might not have anything to do right now.
Back on the event detail page, we begin with content planning! The first step is topic selection. Click "Select Topic".
A view opens with various topic categories.
The default view shows a list, but we use the Heat Map for a better overview. Because who doesn't love a good heat map?
The Heat Map is a two-dimensional matrix that visualizes topics by their popularity and recency.
Light colors show popular topics, basically the rockstars among architecture topics.
Darker colors show less frequently chosen topics. The underdogs who also deserve a chance.
This helps with strategic topic planning based on participant interests.
We select a topic from the Heat Map by clicking on a cell. The system marks the selection and displays details.
After confirmation, the system saves the chosen topic and automatically opens the speaker brainstorming view.
The system is like a good assistant, it always knows what comes next!
Now we collect potential speakers for the chosen topic!
In this phase, we create a pool of candidates we'll contact later. We add four speaker candidates.
This gives us enough options for outreach, in case not everyone accepts.
Because speakers are like cats - sometimes they just say no for no reason at all.
After adding all candidates, we click "Continue to Outreach".
The system automatically switches to the Kanban view, where we can track contact status. Kanban!
That sounds important and organized!
We're now in the speaker outreach phase. The Kanban board shows multiple columns that represent the workflow.
From "Who's that?" through "Contacted" to "Hooray, they said yes!" This visualization gives a quick overview of the progress in speaker acquisition.
Now we systematically contact all speaker candidates.
For each candidate, we click on the card and open the contact dialog.
This documentation is important for tracking and for other team members who need to check the status.
Otherwise next week someone asks: "Did we contact them already?" And nobody knows. Chaos avoided!
After receiving positive responses, we move speakers through the workflow! It's like Tetris, but with people.
We use drag-and-drop to move cards between columns. We move four speakers to the "READY" column.
In the next step, we move speakers from "READY" to "ACCEPTED". All four READY speakers are moved to ACCEPTED.
Smooth as butter!
Before speakers can submit their content, we need to publish the topic.
We navigate to the "Publishing" tab and click "Publish Topic".
In the lower area, there's a preview of the event on the public page. Nice, right?
Back in the Speakers tab, we now submit presentation content for each speaker. Title, abstract, the usual suspects.
We repeat this process for all three speakers with confirmed presentations. Copy, paste, repeat.
No, just kidding, each speaker has unique content, of course!
After content submission comes quality review. Now that we have the content, we can publish the speakers.
We click "Publish Speakers". And here comes the best part!
Now on the public website, not only the topic is visible, but also the confirmed speakers with their topics.
The world can see it!
Back in the Speakers tab, we now review and approve each submitted presentation. Now we're playing quality control.
Looks good, looks good, that too. We approve all three presentations. Green light for everyone!
For slot assignment, we switch to the Sessions view. Click "Manage Slot Assignments". Now we're getting into the timing!
For quick initial planning, we use the Auto-Assign function. The system performs automatic assignment. Magic!
The system does the work. Manual assignment via drag-and-drop is also possible here.
In case you don't trust the computer or just like moving things around.
After slot assignment, we click "Back to Event".
The final step is agenda publication! The grand finale! Click "Publish Agenda". And...
The event is now fully planned and publicly accessible including detailed agenda! Confetti! Fireworks!
Okay, maybe just in your mind, but still! We made it!
After conducting the event, we archive it for history. Switch to the "Overview" tab and click "Edit".
Time to retire the event.
In the form, select "ARCHIVED" as status. The event was great, but now it's history.
For testing purposes, you can override workflow validation.
Enable the checkbox "Override Workflow Validation" and click "Save".
This is basically the emergency exit, in case things don't go according to plan.
And that completes the full event workflow! From the first idea to the archive, we've made the whole journey together!
You're now an event management pro! Thank you for your attention!
And remember: planning events is fun, at least with the right software! See you next time.
Greetings from Creator Nissim.